Finding Aid for Hannah and Lay Company (Traverse City, Mich.) Records, 1846-1931
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Hannah and Lay Company (Traverse City, Mich.) Records
1846-1931
Hannah and Lay Company (Traverse City, Mich.)
85547 Bb.2/2; BB.2 Outsize
Lumber and mercantile company of Chicago, Illinois and Traverse City, Michigan. Business records include minutes, correspondence, and financial ledgers, daybooks, and journals.
8 linear feet
13 oversize volumes
49 microfilms
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The record group was transferred from the Burton Historical Collection (donor no. 1531 ) which had originally received the records from the company.
The record group is open to research.
The Hannah and Lay Company began as a partnership between Perry Hannah, Albert Tracy Lay, and James Morgan in the burgeoning Chicago lumber trade around the middle of the nineteenth century. At first the company purchased lumber from ships that docked in the Chicago harbor. Hoping to eliminate middle-man profits, the partners hoped to operate their own mill. After some investigation, Hannah and Morgan in 1851 decided to purchase a inactive sawmill in the Grand Traverse Bay area of Michigan as well as surrounding timber-rich acreage. The Hannah and Lay development would provide the foundation for city of Traverse City. The company under the management of Hannah acquired additional property totaling by 1886 45,000 acres of timber land. With the great demand for lumber, the company flourished, but also diversifying its business to include Great Lakes shipping, real estate acquisition, flour milling, banking, and storekeeping. In 1883, the company split into two separate corporate entities: Hannah Lay and Company and Hannah Lay Mercantile Company. For many years, Perry Hannah and Albert Tracy Lay alternated each year in the supervision of their Chicago and Traverse City operations. Eventually, Lay would remain in Chicago and Hannah would make Traverse City his permanent home. Recognizing that the boom in timber would not last forever, Hannah in 1886 wisely sold off his timber interests and devoted his energies to the company's mercantile and related operations. Hannah died in 1904, but the company would continue until 1931 when the Traverse City assets of the company were liquidated.
The records of Hannah Lay Company have been divided into two series: Hannah and Lay Company Business Records and Hannah and Lay Mercantile Company.
The history of the arrangement and appraisal of the Hannah and Lay records has been fully described in an article in the American Archivist (Jan. 1976) by Larry Steck and Francis Blouin.
Subjects:
Chicago (Ill.); General stores--Michigan--Traverse City.; Great Lakes.; Hannah and Lay Company.; Hannah and Lay Mercantile Company.; Labor--Michigan--Traverse City.; Land use--Michigan.; Logging--Michigan.; Lumbering--Michigan.; Real estate business--Michigan.; Shipping--Great Lakes.; Traverse City (Mich.)--Businesses.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Business enterprises--Michigan--Traverse City.; Hannah and Lay Company.; Interiors--Michigan--Traverse City.; Hannah and Lay Merchandising Company.
Genre Terms:
Business records.; Photographs.
- Hannah and Lay Company Business Records
  The Hannah and Lay Company Business Records series dates from 1846 to 1931 and documents both the operation of the company in Chicago and in Traverse City. The series includes correspondence, annual reports, and financial journals, daybooks, and ledgers. In addition, there are records detailing the acquisition of properties in the Grand Traverse area, shipping records, and records of the company store in Traverse City.
  - Corporate minutes, April 9, 1895-January 13, 1931 (Box 1)
    (1-1)
  - Contracts and agreements
    - Undated, 1846-1850 (Box 1)
      (1-2)
    - 1851-1855 (Box 1)
      (1-3)
    - 1856-1857 (Box 1)
      (1-4)
    - 1858-1874 (Box 1)
      (1-5)
  - Correspondence
    - (letterpress book), April 15-September 30, 1881 (Box 1)
      (1-6)
    - Undated, July-August 1885 (Box 1)
      (1-7)
    - September 1885 (Box 1)
      (1-8)
    - November 1885 (Box 1)
      (1-9)
    - December 1885 (Box 1)
      (1-10)
    - January 1886 (Box 1)
      (1-11)
    - February-April 1886 (Box 1)
      (1-12)
    - May 1-15, 1886 (Box 1)
      (1-13)
    - May 16-31, 1886 (Box 1)
      (1-14)
    - June-October 1886 (Box 1)
      (1-15)
    - November-December 1886, 1886 undated (Box 1)
      (1-16)
    - January-February 1887 (Box 1)
      (1-17)
    - March-September 1887 (Box 1)
      (1-18)
    - August-October 1888 (Box 1)
      (1-19)
    - November 1888 (Box 1)
      (1-20)
    - December 1888 (Box 1)
      (1-21)
    - January 1889 (Box 1)
      (1-22)
    - February 1889 (Box 1)
      (1-23)
    - March 1889 (Box 1)
      (1-24)
    - (letterbook), May 1895-May 1904 (Box 1)
      (1-25)
    - 1895-1903 (Box 1)
      (1-26)
    - 1904 (Box 1)
      (1-27)
    - January-June 1905 (Box 1)
      (1-28)
    - July-December 1905 (Box 1)
      (1-29)
    - January-April 1906 (Box 1)
      (1-30)
    - May-August 1906 (Box 1)
      (1-31)
    - September-December 1906 (Box 1)
      (1-32)
    - 1907 (Box 1)
      (1-33)
    - 1910 (Box 1)
      (1-34)
  - Financial Reports
    - Lumber Camp and Boarding House Accounts book, 1858-1861 (Box 1)
      (1-35)
    - Average Meal Time Book, 1869-1870 (Box 1)
      (1-36)
    - Perry Hannah Loan Book, 1883-1906 (Box 1)
      (1-37)
    - Annual Reports
      - 1896-1900 (Box 2)
        (2-1)
      - 1901-1908 (Box 2)
        (2-2)
      - 1909-1910 (Box 2)
        (2-3)
      - 1911-1914 (Box 2)
        (2-4)
      - 1915-1917 (Box 2)
        (2-5)
      - 1918-1919 (Box 2)
        (2-6)
    - Statements of Assets and Liabilities
      - 1897-1900 (Box 2)
        (2-7)
      - 1901-1904 (Box 2)
        (2-8)
      - 1905-1908 (Box 2)
        (2-9)
    - Profit-Loss and Property Sold
      - 1900-1901 (Box 2)
        (2-10)
      - 1902-1904 (Box 2)
        (2-11)
      - 1905-1908 (Box 2)
        (2-12)
    - Monthly Reports
      - May-December 1909 (Box 2)
        (2-13)
      - January-June 1910 (Box 2)
        (2-14)
      - July-December 1910 (Box 2)
        (2-15)
      - January-June 1911 (Box 2)
        (2-16)
      - July-December 1911 (Box 2)
        (2-17)
      - January-June 1912 (Box 2)
        (2-18)
      - July-December 1912 (Box 2)
        (2-19)
      - January-June 1913 (Box 2)
        (2-20)
      - July-December 1913 (Box 2)
        (2-21)
      - January-June 1914 (Box 2)
        (2-22)
      - July-December 1914 (Box 2)
        (2-23)
      - January-June 1915 (Box 2)
        (2-24)
      - May-November 1916 (Box 2)
        (2-25)
      - January-May 1917 (Box 2)
        (2-26)
  - Real Estate Records
    - List of Hannah Lay Lands
      - 1851-1853 (Volume 1)
      - 1870-1881 (Volume 2)
    - Inventory no. 2, Traverse City Village Lots, improved and unimproved, 1891-1895 (Box 2)
      (2-27)
    - Ledger of Traverse City Land Sold, 1889-1900 (Box 2)
    - Plat Book, Traverse City, Perry Hannah's Additions, 1892-1914 (Volume 3)
    - Survey data drawn from first Grand Traverse property owned by HLC, 1887 (Box 3)
      (3-1)
    - List of Property Rented, circa 1894 (Box 3)
      (3-2)
    - Real Estate Inventories
      - 1895-1898 (Box 3)
        (3-3)
      - 1901-1902 (Box 3)
        (3-4)
      - 1903-1904 (Box 3)
        (3-5)
      - 1905-1908 (Box 3)
        (3-6)
    - Traverse City Lot Book, 1895-1929 (Volume 4)
    - Traverse City Unimproved Lot Book, 1904-1928 (Box 3)
      (3-7)
  - Great Lakes Shipping Records
    - S. S. "City of Traverse"
      - Ledger, 1871-1881 (Box 3)
        (3-8)
      - Ledger, 1883-1887 (Box 3)
        (3-9)
      - Day Book, 1878-1883 (Box 3)
        (3-10)
    - S. S. "Clara Ballet" Day Book, 1878-1879 (Box 3)
      (3-11)
    - S. S. "City of Grand Rapids"
      - Day Book, 1882-1884 (Box 3)
        (3-12)
      - Freight Receipts, 1883-1884 (Volume 5)
      - Seaman's Time Book, 1883-1892 (Box 3)
        (3-13)
      - Captain's Account, 1892 (Box 3)
        (3-14)
    - S. S. "Faxton"-Shipping Invoices, 1884 (Volume 6)
  - Grist Mill Inventories, 1924-1926 (Box 4)
    (4-1)
  - General Business Records
    - Journals
      - Chicago
        - 1854-1860 (Volume 7)
        - (incomplete), 1860 (Box 10, Reel 1)
        - 1865 (Box 10, Reel 1)
        - 1870 (Box 10, Reel 1)
        - 1875 (Box 10, Reel 1)
        - 1880 (Box 10, Reel 1)
        - October 1882-September 1883 (Box 10, Reel 1)
    - Ledgers
      - Chicago
        - 1855-1862 (Volume 8)
        - 1855-1861 (Box 10, Reel 2)
        - 1862-1867 (Box 10, Reel 2)
        - 1867-1871 (Box 10, Reel 3)
        - 1871-1874 (Box 10, Reel 3)
        - 1874-1876 (Box 10, Reel 4)
        - 1876-1878 (Box 10, Reel 4)
        - 1878-1881 (Box 10, Reel 5)
        - 1881-1884 (Box 10, Reel 5)
      - Traverse City
        - 1852-1854 (Volume 9)
        - 1854-1856 (Volume 10)
        - 1858-1860 (Box 10, Reel 6)
        - 1860-1862 (Box 10, Reel 6)
        - 1864-1866 (Box 10, Reel 7)
        - 1868-1871 (Box 10, Reel 8)
        - 1875-1877 (Box 10, Reel 8)
        - 1879-1880 (Box 10, Reel 9)
        - 1880-1881 (Box 10, Reel 9)
        - 1882-1883 (Box 10, Reel 10)
        - 1884-1885 (Box 10, Reel 10)
        - 1885-1886 (Box 10, Reel 11)
        - 1889-1890 (Box 10, Reel 12)
        - 1890-1891 (Box 10, Reel 13)
        - 1894-1895 (Box 10, Reel 13)
        - 1895-1897 (Box 10, Reel 14)
        - 1899-1902 (Box 10, Reel 14)
      - Miscellaneous accounts
        - I, 1905-1925 (Box 10, Reel 15)
        - II, 1905-1925 (Box 10, Reel 16)
        - III, 1905-1925 (Box 10, Reel 17)
    - Cash Books
      - Chicago
        - 1851-1861 (Box 4)
          (4-2)
        - 1860 (Box 10, Reel 18)
        - 1865 (Box 10, Reel 18)
        - 1870 (Box 10, Reel 18)
        - 1875 (Box 10, Reel 18)
        - 1880 (Box 10, Reel 18)
        - October 1882-September 1883 (Box 10, Reel 18)
        - 1885 (Box 10, Reel 18)
      - Traverse City
        - 1870 (Box 10, Reel 19)
        - 1875 (Box 10, Reel 19)
        - 1880 (Box 10, Reel 19)
        - October 1882-September 1883 (Box 10, Reel 19)
        - 1885 (Box 10, Reel 20)
        - 1895 (Box 10, Reel 20)
          (1890 data missing in original)
        - 1900 (Box 10, Reel 20)
        - 1905 (Box 10, Reel 20)
    - Daybooks
      - Chicago
        - 1852-1854 (Volume 11)
        - 1855-1856 (Box 4)
          (4-3)
        - 1860 (Box 10, Reel 21)
        - 1865 (Box 10, Reel 21)
        - 1870 (Box 10, Reel 21)
        - 1875 (Box 10, Reel 21)
        - 1880 (Box 10, Reel 22)
        - October 1882-September 1883 (Box 10, Reel 22)
        - 1885 (Box 10, Reel 23)
          (incomplete)
      - Traverse City
        - 1852-1853 (Box 4)
          (4-4)
        - 1853-1854 (Box 4)
          (4-5)
        - 1854, 2 folders (Box 4)
          (4-6; 4-7)
        - 1854-1855 (Box 4)
          (4-8)
        - 1860 (Box 10, Reel 23)
        - 1865 (Box 10, Reel 23)
        - 1870 (Box 10, Reel 24)
        - 1875 (Box 10, Reel 24)
        - 1880 (Box 10, Reel 24)
        - October 1882-September 1883 (Box 10, Reel 25)
        - 1885 (Box 10, Reel 25)
        - 1890 (Box 10, Reel 26)
        - 1895 (Box 10, Reel 26)
        - 1900 (Box 10, Reel 26)
        - 1905 (Box 10, Reel 26)
      - Traverse City Store
        - 1857-1858 (Box 4)
          (4-9)
        - 1858-1859 (Box 5)
          (5-1)
        - 1859 (Box 5)
          (5-2)
        - October 1882-September 1883 (Box 10, Reel 27)
    - Miscellaneous
      - 1910 (Box 10, Reel 27)
      - 1915 (Box 10, Reel 27)
      - 1920 (Box 10, Reel 28)
      - 1925 (Box 10, Reel 28)
- Hannah Lay Mercantile Company
  The second series - Hannah and Lay Mercantile Company -- details the diversification of the company into the retail business, and includes annual reports, correspondence, sales reports, financial records, invoices, and related materials. The series dates from 1883 to 1931.
  - Corporate Minutes
    - May 29, 1883-June 21, 1906 (Box 5)
      (5-3)
    - June 21, 1906-January 31, 1931 (Box 5)
      (5-4)
  - Annual Reports of General Manager and/or Secretary
    - 1885-1888 (Box 5)
      (5-5)
    - 1889-1891 (Box 5)
      (5-6)
    - 1892-1894 (Box 5)
      (5-7)
    - 1895-1897 (Box 5)
      (5-8)
    - 1898-1900 (Box 5)
      (5-9)
    - 1901-1903 (Box 5)
      (5-10)
    - 1904-1905 (Box 5)
      (5-11)
  - Correspondence
    - December 1901-February 1907 (Box 5)
      (5-12)
    - 1910-1916 (Box 5)
      (5-13)
    - 1917 (Box 5)
      (5-14)
    - 1918 (Box 5)
      (5-15)
    - January-October 1919 (Box 5)
      (5-16)
    - November-December 1919 (Box 5)
      (5-17)
    - January 1920 (Box 5)
      (5-18)
    - February 1920 (Box 5)
      (5-19)
    - March 1920 (Box 5)
      (5-20)
    - April 1920 (Box 5)
      (5-21)
    - May 1920 (Box 5)
      (5-22)
    - June 1920 (Box 5)
      (5-23)
    - July 1920 (Box 5)
      (5-24)
    - August 1920 (Box 5)
      (5-25)
    - September 1920 (Box 5)
      (5-26)
    - October 1920 (Box 6)
      (6-1)
    - November 1920 (Box 6)
      (6-2)
    - December 1920 (Box 6)
      (6-3)
    - Undated, January 1921 (Box 6)
      (6-4)
    - February 1921 (Box 6)
      (6-5)
    - March 1921 (Box 6)
      (6-6)
    - April 1921 (Box 6)
      (6-7)
    - May 1921 (Box 6)
      (6-8)
    - June 1921 (Box 6)
      (6-9)
    - July 1921 (Box 6)
      (6-10)
    - August 1921 (Box 6)
      (6-11)
    - September 1921 (Box 6)
      (6-12)
    - October 1921 (Box 6)
      (6-13)
    - November 1921 (Box 6)
      (6-14)
    - December 1921 (Box 6)
      (6-15)
    - Undated, January 1922 (Box 6)
      (6-16)
    - February 1922 (Box 6)
      (6-17)
    - March 1922 (Box 6)
      (6-18)
    - April 1922 (Box 6)
      (6-19)
    - May 1922 (Box 6)
      (6-20)
    - June 1922 (Box 6)
      (6-21)
    - July 1922 (Box 6)
      (6-22)
    - August 1922 (Box 6)
      (6-23)
    - September 1-15, 1922 (Box 6)
      (6-24)
    - September 16-30, 1922 (Box 6)
      (6-25)
    - October 1-15, 1922 (Box 6)
      (6-26)
    - October 16-31, 1922 (Box 6)
      (6-27)
    - November 1922 (Box 6)
      (6-28)
    - December 1922 (Box 6)
      (6-29)
    - Undated, January 1923 (Box 6)
      (6-30)
    - February 1923 (Box 6)
      (6-31)
    - March 1923 (Box 6)
      (6-32)
    - April 1923 (Box 6)
      (6-33)
    - May-June 1923 (Box 6)
      (6-34)
    - July 1923 (Box 6)
      (6-35)
    - August 1923 (Box 6)
      (6-36)
    - September-October 1923 (Box 6)
      (6-37)
    - November-December 1923 (Box 6)
      (6-38)
    - Undated, January 1924 (Box 6)
      (6-39)
    - February-March 1924 (Box 6)
      (6-40)
    - April-May 1924 (Box 6)
      (6-41)
    - June 1924 (Box 6)
      (6-42)
    - July 1924 (Box 6)
      (6-43)
    - August-September 1924 (Box 6)
      (6-44)
    - October-December 1924 (Box 6)
      (6-45)
    - December 1925 (Box 6)
      (6-46)
  - Miscellaneous Business Records
    - Monthly Personnel Payrolls, November 1882-February 1902 (Volume 12)
    - Personnel Lists, 1883; 1890; 1896 (Box 7)
      (7-1)
    - Comparative Statements (Assets/Liabilities)
      - 1892-1893 (Box 7)
        (7-2)
      - 1893-1894 (Box 7)
        (7-3)
      - 1894-1895 (Box 7)
        (7-4)
      - 1895-1896 (Box 7)
        (7-5)
      - 1896-1897 (Box 7)
        (7-6)
      - 1897-1898 (Box 7)
        (7-7)
      - 1898-1899 (Box 7)
        (7-8)
      - 1899-1900 (Box 7)
        (7-9)
      - 1900-1901 (Box 7)
        (7-10)
      - 1901-1902 (Box 7)
        (7-11)
      - 1902-1903 (Box 7)
        (7-12)
      - 1903-1904 (Box 7)
        (7-13)
      - 1905-1906 (Box 7)
        (7-14)
    - Statement of Estimated Worth, 1893-1897 (Box 7)
      (7-15)
    - Monthly Divisional Reports
      - 1907 (Box 7)
        (7-16)
      - 1908 (Box 7)
        (7-17)
      - 1909 (Box 7)
        (7-18)
      - 1910 (Box 7)
        (7-19)
      - 1911 (Box 7)
        (7-20)
      - 1917 (Box 7)
        (7-21)
      - 1918 (Box 7)
        (7-22)
      - 1919 (Box 7)
        (7-23)
      - 1920 (Box 8)
        (8-1)
      - 1921 (Box 8)
        (8-2)
    - Merchandise Balances, 1903 (Box 8)
      (8-3)
    - Departmental Reports of Sales
      - 1907-1910 (Box 8)
        (8-4)
      - 1911-1914 (Box 8)
        (8-5)
      - 1915-1920 (Box 8)
        (8-6)
      - 1921-1927 (Box 8)
        (8-7)
    - Salesmen's Reports
      - 1910-1916 (Box 8)
        (8-8)
      - 1917-1927 (Box 8)
        (8-9)
    - Monthly Reports (Total Sales/Total Purchases)
      - 1907-1910 (Box 8)
        (8-10)
      - 1911-1914 (Box 8)
        (8-11)
      - 1915-1919 (Box 8)
        (8-12)
      - 1920-1924 (Box 8)
        (8-13)
      - 1925-1928 (Box 8)
        (8-14)
    - Sales Reports
      - 1907-1916 (Box 8)
        (8-15)
      - 1917-1920 (Box 8)
        8-16)
      - 1921-1923 (Box 8)
        (8-17)
      - 1924-1926 (Box 8)
        (8-18)
    - Miscellaneous Patent Information (Box 8)
      (8-19)
  - Company Scrapbook, 1905-1907 (Box 8)
    (8-20)
  - Blueprints of Company Store, undated (Box 8)
    (8-21)
  - Photographs (Box 8)
    Streetfront view of store and interior photo showing displays and arrangement of merchandise.
    (8-22)
  - General Business Records
    - Journals
      - October 1882-September 1883 (Box 10, Reel 29)
      - 1885 (Box 10, Reel 29)
      - 1890 (Box 10, Reel 29)
      - 1895 (Box 10, Reel 30)
      - 1900 (Box 10, Reel 30)
      - 1905 (Box 10, Reel 30)
      - 1910 (Box 10, Reel 30)
      - 1915 (Box 10, Reel 30)
    - Ledgers
      - 1883 (Box 10, Reel 31)
      - 1884-1885 (Box 10, Reel 31)
      - 1889-1890 (Box 10, Reel 32)
      - 1894-1895 (Box 10, Reel 33)
      - 1895-1896 (Box 10, Reel 34)
      - 1900 (Box 10, Reel 35)
      - 1904-1905 (Box 10, Reel 36)
      - 1905-1906 (Box 10, Reel 37)
    - Invoice Records
      - 1878-1882 (Box 10, Reel 38)
      - 1882-1885 (Box 10, Reel 38)
      - 1885-1888 (Box 10, Reel 39)
      - 1888-1890 (Box 10, Reel 39)
      - 1892-1893 (Box 10, Reel 39)
      - 1893-1895 (Box 10, Reel 40)
      - 1895-1897 (Box 10, Reel 40)
      - 1897-1899 (Box 10, Reel 40)
      - 1899-1901 (Box 10, Reel 41)
      - 1901-1903 (Box 10, Reel 41)
      - 1903-1904 (Box 10, Reel 41)
      - 1904-1906 (Box 10, Reel 42)
      - 1906-1908 (Box 10, Reel 42)
      - 1908-1909 (Box 10, Reel 42)
      - 1909-1910 (Box 10, Reel 42)
      - 1911-1915 (Box 10, Reel 43)
      - 1927-1928 (Box 10, Reel 43)
    - Sales Distribution, General (monthly)
      - 1910 (Box 10, Reel 43)
      - 1915 (Box 10, Reel 43)
      - 1925 (Box 10, Reel 43)
      - 1930 (Box 10, Reel 43)
    - Sales Distribution, General (daily)
      - 1910 (Box 10, Reel 43)
      - 1915 (Box 10, Reel 44)
      - 1920 (Box 10, Reel 44)
      - 1925 (Box 10, Reel 45)
    - Remittance Registers
      - 1890 (Box 10, Reel 45)
      - 1895 (Box 10, Reel 45)
      - 1900 (Box 10, Reel 45)
      - 1905 (Box 10, Reel 45)
    - Bills Receivable Record
      - 1886-1892 (Box 10, Reel 45)
      - 1889-1893 (Box 10, Reel 45)
      - 1891-1896 (Box 10, Reel 45)
      - 1892-1901 (Box 10, Reel 46)
      - 1894-1907 (Box 10, Reel 46)
    - Vouchers Audited
      - 1910 (Box 10, Reel 46)
      - 1915 (Box 10, Reel 47)
      - 1920 (Box 10, Reel 48)
      - 1925 (Box 10, Reel 49)
    - Payrolls, 1915-1917 (Box 10, Reel 49)
    - Certificates of Stocks (Volume 13)
- Master Negative Microfilm (Box 9)